<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Great Britains remembrancer, looking in and out. Tending to the increase of the monies of the Commonwealth· / Presented to his Highness the Lord Protector, and to the High Court of Parliament now assembled. By the author Ralphe Maddison, Kt.</title>
            <title>Englands looking in and out.</title>
            <author>Maddison, Ralph, Sir.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89225</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E818_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202851</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863008</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863008</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115190</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89225)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115190)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 124:E818[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Great Britains remembrancer, looking in and out. Tending to the increase of the monies of the Commonwealth· / Presented to his Highness the Lord Protector, and to the High Court of Parliament now assembled. By the author Ralphe Maddison, Kt.</title>
                  <title>Englands looking in and out.</title>
                  <author>Maddison, Ralph, Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Newcomb, and are to be sold by Humphrey Moseley, at the Prince's Arms in St. Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655. [i.e. 1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An expanded version of: Englands looking in and out.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb:"; the second 5 in imprint date has been crossed out and date altered to 1654.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Money --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Taxation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115190:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>GREAT BRITAINS</hi> Remembrancer, <hi>Looking In and Out.</hi> Tending to the Increaſe of the MONIES OF THE COMMONWEALTH.</p>
            <p>Preſented to his Highneſs the <hi>LORD PROTECTOR,</hi> And to the High Court of <hi>PARLIAMENT</hi> Now Aſſembled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Author</hi> RALPHE MADDISON, <hi>K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Newcomb,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> at the <hi>Prince's Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:115190:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115190:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO His Highneſs the</hi> Lord Protector <hi>of</hi> England, Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>And to the High Court of</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament <hi>now aſſembled.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MAy it pleaſe your Highneſs and this Honorable Parliament: Two potent paſſions do extremely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault me at once, Grief and Deſire. Grief to ſee the walls of our City ſo much waſted, and the ſinews of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth ſo much enfeebled, by the exporting our monies of late years coyned, the quantity whereof will truly appear, if you pleaſe to be certified from the Records of the Mint; it is given out many Millions almoſt all exported but our worne and clipt ſilver, and moſt of our Gold: The Mint at a late ſtand; which one thing were ſufficient to overthrow our Commonwealth, and to bring us under the command of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. And the ſtand of the Mint had continued, if the Prizes taken from the <hi>Dutch</hi> by our Sea-ſword had not ſet it a-work; and will ſtand again, if remedy be not had, both in providing work for the Mint, and keeping our monies from unlawful exportation when we have it. I humbly conceive the Remedy is feaſable, for the like hath been done heretofore when it was evil with us: It was cured by the hand and rule of a Woman, whoſe fame and name will never dye. To ſpeak briefly, ſhe baniſhed baſe monies out of <hi>England,</hi> ſhe ſet the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> at liberty, by ſending an Army of men, and monies to relieve them, and lent more then a Million to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Low-Country men. The like ſhe did to the Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants of <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> after ſirnamed <hi>Henry le grand,</hi> for whom I my ſelf did lift up my right hand: who after the
<pb facs="tcp:115190:3"/>ſtroke of ſeventeen Battles in his own perſon, obtained the Crown of <hi>France.</hi> Beſides, ſhe had long wars in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and fourteen years Sea-Wars with <hi>Spain,</hi> to ſome whereof I was an eye-witneſs. She dyed rich in good debts owing her, rich in love of her Subjects, her purſe was not empty, and her Land at her death full of Coin and Silver-Plate, which was coined lately, the Mint-Records can tell when. This I recount with grief to have ſeen our Mint ſtanding, and likely to ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. The want of obtaining and retention of this good Food of arts and labour, the ſinews of war, and fomenter of peace, will make a publique heart to ſorrow and grieve.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs my Deſire, mixt with hope, doth abate the grief. What is paſt cannot be recalled, but errors paſt may be amended For the which I humbly preſent to your Highneſs and this Honorable Aſſembly ſome crude or indigeſted Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals, by your wiſdoms to be altered, fortified and amended, as your Highneſs and this Honorable Aſſembly ſhall think fit and commodious for theſe times. And whereas heretofore two things were propounded under the Kingly government, <hi>viz.</hi> The Merchants Exchange, and the Ballance of Trade; and now three things more under a Commonwealth, <hi>viz.</hi> A Bank, a Councel of Mint-affairs, Free Ports: A ſhort reaſon may be given, which I humbly refer to your Highneſs judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. VVhen Governments do change, Reaſons do change likewiſe. The differences between a Monarchy and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth are many and great, which I refer to <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> to expatiate. So praying to God to proſper your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in all happineſs, I remain.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble and devoted Suppliant,</hi>
Ralphe Maddiſon, <hi>K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115190:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I enter into the particular Diſcourſe of Mynt-affairs, I do humbly conceive in the firſt place, it behoveth to ſhew the compoſing of Weights of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and Gold; without the knowledge of which, no Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Mynt-cauſes can be underſtood.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. I. <hi>Compoſing of Weights.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SIlver weight is thus compoſed: A pound Troy containeth 12 Ounces, an Ounce containeth twenty Penny weight, a Penny weight containeth 24 grains of Wheat, taken out of the midſt of the Wheat-ear; and <hi>è converſe,</hi> 24 Grains taken out of the midſt of the Wheat-ear, doe make a Penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weight; Twenty-penny weight do make an Ounce, and 12 Ounces doe make a Pound Troy. Where note, that a Pound Tale is but 4 Ounces, which before King <hi>Henry</hi> the 6. his time was all one with a pound Troy; He then raiſed it by Prerogative to 30 Pence the Ounce, which cauſed the price of an Ounce of Silver to paſs at that price in currant pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between man and man; and a pound weight Troy to paſs at 30 Pence, which before was but 20 Pence. Thus by dividing the Ounce Troy into ſo many more prices, he loſt ſo much in his Revenues, Cuſtoms and other Duties belonging to him, as he had multiplyed his Pence in number; and this is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115190:4"/>called raiſing of the Coin in Denomination.</p>
               <p>And in ſucceſs of time between <hi>Henry</hi> the 6. and <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. his time, the Ounce was raiſed to 60 pence, and ſo it remaineth ever ſince conſtant, notwithſtanding the raiſing of it in Foraign parts. For it was found by experience of our former rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,
<note place="margin">A temporary remedy is but a fallacie.</note> that raiſing of the Ounce Troy was but a Temporary remedy to keep the Mony at home, and ſtood in ſtead, or continued no longer then they rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed again beyond-Seas. This may ſuffice for the weight of Silver conſiſting of 60 pence the Ounce Troy, 12 Ounces to the pound Troy.</p>
               <p>The Gold pound being the ſame in weight with the Silver is otherwiſe compoſed in other terms, as thus. The Gold caſteth away the name of Penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weight thus. A pound weight of Troy of pure Gold is ſaid to contain or conſiſt of 24 Carrats, and every Carrat containeth 4 Grains, 2 Carrats and an Ounce are one weight; A Grain, and half a quarter of an Ounce, are one weight.</p>
               <p>Next followeth in order to know the compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the mixture or fineneſs of Gold and Silver; and firſt of Silver, becauſe it is the common Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-man both at home and abroad.</p>
               <p>Here is to be noted, That no Monies be made of pure Silver in no Mynts; the reaſon is, becauſe in its purity the Silver is as flexible as Lead almoſt; and therefore not ſo uſefull in its purity, as when it is ſomething hardned with Copper; even ſo it is with Gold: There is no pure Gold minted in any place I know of, but hath ſome allay or Copper.</p>
               <p>And if it hath been ſo heretofore, it is ſo ancient, that no memory thereof remaineth to us. And if it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115190:4"/>were at any time done ſo, the alteration began with ſome Prince that meant and did deceive others by ſo doing: For it is a powerfull means to fetch his neighbours Coin from them to be mynted in his Mynt; which being perceived, his Neighbours did mix their Coines alſo, thinking thereby to fetch theirs home again by the ſame means it went away.</p>
               <p>But as it is before ſaid of Denomination, ſo then and now it falleth out to be the ſame in debaſing the Coin as it was in Denomination, but a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary remedy, and to no purpoſe, but extreme hurt, as I ſhall tell you hereafter, when I come to ſpeak of the inconveniences of raiſing the Coin by Denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or debaſing of it by Allay or Copper, which will be all one, and worketh alike in effect.</p>
               <p>So then, you having the weights of Gold and Silver, and compoſition thereof in your underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and memory, it remaineth to let you know, That almoſt all Princes Coins do differ in fineneſs or mixture. Few do agree juſt together, in as much as <hi>Spain</hi> (when it had the Kingdom of <hi>Portugall</hi>) had four Mynts and more under his Dominions or Command. Two in the Weſt-Indies, <hi>Mexico</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> and two in the Continent of <hi>Spain, Lisbon</hi> and <hi>Sivile;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Difference of fineneſſe.</note> yet all four differ in fineneſs one from the other ſomething, for which there is ſome reaſon to be given in its proper time. So likewiſe there is ſome difference in fineneſs in other Princes Coins; as between us and France, and the Low-Countreys, Archdukes and United Provinces, <hi>Lubeck, Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough, Stoad,</hi> and the Emperiall Cities of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</p>
               <p>And for this cauſe of differences, ours conſiſting
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115190:5"/>of eleven Ounces,
<note place="margin">Moſt Mynts differ in fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> 2 penny weight fine. <hi>France</hi> of eleven Ounces fine, Low-Countreys of ten Ounces and ſome of nine Ounces fine in the pound Troy.</p>
               <p>It behoveth us who have the fineſt ſtandard or mixture of Silver in our Moneys, to beware that our fine Moneys be not drawn out from us to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the baſer Mynts. For if Denomination have a power to work that effect, much more hath Emba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Coin, being not ſo eaſily perceived as the other, and to watch over them in all places, leaſt we be deceived by any of them: Or elſe how ſhould we know when they alter, or what Mynt it is that draweth our Moneys from us: Therefore it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to watch.</p>
               <p>But ſome will ſay, what need we be put to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to watch others, cannot we more eaſily do what others do.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, If there were no harm in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at home, yet to alter with them that alter, or may alter, requireth a continuall watch over all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with whom we have Commerce: And if we ſhould alter our Mynt, as often as others may alter, we ſhould ever be altering, and have no reſt at home. This by conſequence muſt needs bring a confuſion in ſhort time, when once moving our Mynt hath made great alterations amongſt us at home, and will ever do ſo when we ſhall alter. It is the greateſt harm to Superior and Subjects as ſhall be ſhewed God willing hereafter.</p>
               <p>In the mean time give me leave to let you know that in or about the year of our Lord, 1555. We being in amity with all Princes and Neighbor-Mynts, there was a generall conſent amongſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115190:5"/>and States to make a Treaty for the concord in Mynt-affairs, to keep a parity in Coins; which Treaties were frequent in Elder times, but now by reaſon of Wars near hand in <hi>France, Low-countries</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> is omitted.</p>
               <p>And in K. <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth's time, there is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of A Treatiſe between the King and the Archdutcheſs of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> wherein it was found that the difference of an Half-penny in an Angel of Gold, would be ſufficient to exhauſt his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure out of his Kingdom, and by no means would ſuffer it.</p>
               <p>Then per conſequence what doe they which at this time do raiſe their Mony twenty in the hundred above others.</p>
               <p>The anſwer to this is, They do break the Law of Nations, which is a juſt cauſe of war among Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to goe about to draw away their Neighbours Coin by enhancing by Denomination, or debaſing the fineneſs by Allay; for all make one effect as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>But what care they to break the Law of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that purpoſe to have War; and this is advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous for that purpoſe of War, to draw Money to themſelves, and from whom they do War with. Then is anſwered for that point, and muſt we then of conſequence have our Moneys exhauſted (as they are) or make War, and by the next conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence be und one: Is there no other remedy? There is, but that is referred to another time and place.</p>
               <p>Now I have laid open the compoſing of the weight and fineneſs of Gold and ſilver, I am to ſhew the cauſe of Exporting of our Gold and Silver, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Remedy can be applyed.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115190:6"/>
               <p>And this is a ſecret to moſt men to know the cauſe, and will be controverted by them that have profit by it; and if we believe them that contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it, the cauſe is loſt: Therefore I pray remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> ſaith, as concerning Merchant-Exchange, or touching Exchange: <hi>Truſt not a Merchant in the buſineſs of Exchange, or touching Exchange; A Laborer in the point of Hire; nor a Souldier in the ending of Wars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bear in minde, I pray you, and have it habitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in you, the weight of Gold and Silver, and the fineneſs of our own Coin eſpecially, without the which knowing and remembring, no man can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Merchandizing Exchange, the true cauſe of exhauſting of our Moneys, nor yet the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy thereof: Therefore I pray you pauſe upon that awhile, which hath bin delivered, unleſs you have bin verſed in, or do underſtand the Mynt-bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; and compoſing both weight and fineneſs of Gold and Silver, which hath bin in ſome meaſure declared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. <hi>II.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw by your favour, becauſe theſe words (<hi>viz.</hi> Ballance of Trade or Commerce and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizing Exchange) muſt of force be mentioned, being the words of Art or Science well known to many in this Honourable Aſſembly, who have bin verſed by Trade or Travel in Foraign parts: Yet becauſe I ſuppoſe there be more here aſſembled that have not been verſed in, or given their minds to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115190:6"/>Merchandizing buſineſs, I humbly crave pardon if I be bold (for the help of all mens underſtanding herein) to explain theſe words in as few words as I can.</p>
               <p>And firſt of Ballance.
<note place="margin">Ballance of Trade.</note> All men do know what it meaneth at home in buying and ſelling, but the word Trade put thereto, is obſcure till it be opened. Ballance of Trade then is the computation or tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the accompt or valuation of all the Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize exported or imported into this Comon-wealth every year; which being caſt up, may tell us whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we get or loſe, or what loſſe or gain cometh to the Commonwealth that year the Ballance is caſt up. And if it be found, that we import more then we export, then that which doth want of making the Ballance equall, muſt be fulfilled with our Commonwealths ſtock or ſtore of Money, which in proceſs of time will eat up or conſume to a very ſmall portion our Moneys, that ſhould beate or maintain our home-Commerce or Markets, and per conſequence leſſen the prizes of our Wools, Corn, Lands, and what not: For this is infallibly true in common ſenſe, That where much money is, there the prizes are greater; and where little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is, there the prizes of all things are leſs, and grow low. Hence it was &amp; wil be ſaid this Proverb, <hi>Regina pecunia donat,</hi> for money will bear rule in price in deſpight of all men that ſay no. But I doe conjecture (as ſome have ſaid to my ſelf) ſome in this Aſſembly will ſay, How is it poſſible that all Goods or Merchandizes going out of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and coming in, ſhould be accounted? This is a thing that to ſome Wiſe men doth ſeem impoſſible.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115190:7"/>
               <p>To this I anſwer, it is no new thing the Valuation or rate or price of all Goods going out and into this Realm, hath been put in Books duly kept in every port of this Realm, and once a year brought into the Kings Remembrancers office in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, and there to be collected and made up into one groſs Summ of all out-bound, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sum of all in-bound Goods: Whereby the King might (as in a Mirror) ſee the face of his Commonwealth, whether it grew fat or lean; and this (under favourable correction be it ſpoken) was one amongſt other cauſes, wherefore Cuſtome of old was due to the King by common Reaſon or law for the maintenance of the Officers that attend this care in every Port, and is ſo ancient, That in <hi>Henry</hi> the third his time it was called the Old Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, before all memory of Record. This may ſuffice in brevity for the words Ballance of Trade.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Merchant-Exchange.</note> the word Exchange, all know what it is to make a change. Merchandizing Exchange is known only to Merchants, and to thoſe who in Forraign Travail have uſed it: And few of either ſort doe know the par or equall Exchange of Coins between Forainers and us.</p>
               <p>Exchange of Merchants was firſt invented for the ſaving of Portage, and keeping of Moneys at home in every Government or Commonwealth; beſides the hazard that might befall in carrying of Treaſure as luggage from place to place, which otherwiſe upon every ſeverall Contract made to be paid forraignly, would be exported, and every Travailer beyond the Sea ſhould carry his expend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Money with him. But now if by equall or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantageous
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115190:7"/>Exchange, a man deliver an hundred pounds here, to be paid ſo much like quantity of Gold or Silver there again beyond Seas, this both keepeth the Money at home as aforeſaid, and ſaveth the hazard in carriage. But if by unequal exchange a gain may be had by over-valuing of our Monies beyond Sea, as now they be overvalued, eſpecially in <hi>France,</hi> not only a Merchant making contract as aforeſaid, or a Travailer not knowing the myſterie ſhall loſe Ten or more in the hundred; and the Merchant-obſerver of the myſterie (for the gain had thereby) export the Money in ſpecie, but more ſpecially Gold, when viſibly without change of the ſpecies, he may retain ten of thoſe Pieces, or more in the Hundred; and there with 90 Pieces pay the Hundred pieces received here; and this is the overt or open fallacy, now too frequent in <hi>France,</hi> practiſed upon, or by the Denomination of that Coin.</p>
               <p>But there is another more ſecret which is practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Exchangers, to be conſidered from the fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Coin: Wherein is to be noted, that all Princes Coins are not alike, for ſome have more Allay or Copper mixt with the Gold or Silver, which were a long Diſcourſe to enter into, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on agitation of this buſineſs of Exchange will be opened ſufficiently. There being only two chief wayes of deceit, Denomination or open deceit, the ſecond intrinſick or inward value, conſiſting in the mixture of Copper more or leſs put into the Gold or Silver.</p>
               <p>Alſo take this with you for a Principle, That Moneys can neither be advanced in Denomination,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115190:8"/>nor a pound Troy, or an Ounce be made into more pieces of ſilver, nor debaſed by putting more Copper or Allay, without generall detriment to the Republique; a perillous thing to deal withall without doubt, and moſt ſpecially in Land Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweals.</p>
               <p>And wherefore more in Land Commonweals, then in Maritime and Merchandizing Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weals; You muſt be told, or you will not believe. Merchants can immediatly change with the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger without detriment. The Merchant can imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſet price of his Merchandize according to the worth of the Money, and the Artificer and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer ſet a price according to his labour or hire, which cannot be done in a Land-ſtate, more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in our Commonwealth, which I forbear for the preſent, till I ſhew the inconveniences or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs that would follow the alteration of our Mynt, and will be moſt pernicious to undertake any ſuch thing.</p>
               <p>Moreover, becauſe our Gold might not be ſeen too viſibly, and make too great a ſhew in France, or elſwhere, there is order to bring in the Foraign Gold ſo faſt as may be to be re-Mynted again in their Mynts. In <hi>France</hi> they doe Mynt double and treble, and quatreble Pieces, calling them <hi>Lowyzens,</hi> and mynt them after the proportion of Fifteen to One of ſilver. We holding in our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion Thirteen to One, or a little more; which very Mynt is able by that means to draw all our Gold away, even that which is left, ſo faſt as can be gleaned, if Remedy be not provided therein.</p>
               <p>Now this Obſervation following offereth it ſelf
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115190:8"/>to give us to underſtand, That if this proportion between Gold and Silver be not obſerved aright, Gold may buy out Silver, and Silver may buy out Gold out of the Realm, and ſo the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth be deprived of both: The raiſing of Gold here did cauſe more Gold then Silver to come to the Mynt, and by the ſame means it is called from us into <hi>France,</hi> which plainly ſheweth that the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Gold or Silver, or diſproportioning one by another, is but temporary, and proveth no better in the end then a fallacy, as enhancing and deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and ſo they all be. And the truth is, no State ſtands ſure that ſtands not on the grounds and rules of right.</p>
               <p>Here is to be noted, that Silver prizes Gold, and Gold prizes not Silver; the reaſon is, becauſe Silver is of more common uſe (though Gold be more eſteemed of Rich men) according to the common Adage, <hi>Bonum quo communius eo melius.</hi> It is alſo better for the Commonwealth that more Silver then Gold be mynted; for Silver is not ſo haſtily nor eaſily exported as Gold will be. And there will be alwayes ſome Canker-worms or Money-Brokers to export Silver or Gold, ſo long as Trade is: For remedy of which, there muſt be ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance made in the Balance of Trade, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all diligent watch that may be, and great Reward to be given to the diſcoverers.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115190:9"/>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP III.</head>
               <p>BUt ſomtehing elſe cometh to mind which is, the inconveniences that befall our ſtate, when our Monies are raiſed or made little, the moving of our Mintmuſt either be in embaſing the Gold or Sylver, or advancing it in denomination or diminiſhing it by the ſheares. But back it cannot be brought when once it is raiſed and hath obtained currency. It is a dangerous thing to meddle with the Mint, either in embaſing the monies, or cutting it ſmaller with the ſheares, or making it lighter: for if it be embaſed; firſt it cauſeth counterfeiting ſecondly, that part (as ſo much as is embaſed) will carry ſo much fine ſilver out of the land; and when it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, the amends is as evill as the diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>All thoſe in whoſe hands the baſe monies ſhall be, will be the loſers of ſo much as is minted within the land, before it be decryed and what grievance would this be, able to cauſe the commonalty to hate the Government, and fall into uproars and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall rebelions, as it hath bin in times paſt, when the Commons rebelled in <hi>Henry</hi> the 6 his time, and wrote theſe words in their banner or ſtandard, <hi>Rex eſt qui bene regit.</hi> This and ſome other miſtakes and misgovernments, was the means that ſet the Crown on <hi>Edward</hi> the fourths head.</p>
               <p>The like inconvenience to embaſing, cometh by coining of Farthing-tokens, and giving them cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency and decrying them.</p>
               <p>If the money be made leſſe, it giveth ſo much to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115190:9"/>the leſſee, Farmer, or borrower. All revenues that ſtand upon conſtant fees of this Common-wealth; as Cuſtomes, Impoſts, Taxes, &amp; ſuch like ancient leaſes, or rent charges; all ſuch as be leaſed ſhall loſe ſo much; the Noble-man, Gentle-man, and Uſurer ſhall part with ſo much; in proportion as the monie is advanced; in ſo much force is raiſing of monie, by often raifing from 20<abbr>
                     <hi>d</hi>
                  </abbr> to 5<abbr>
                     <hi>s</hi>
                  </abbr> the ounce as it hath altered the places of Common juſtice: and this is not all the inconvenience; price of vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls will be advanced accordingly, and all wages raiſed, and good reaſon for it. So whether monies be raiſed or embaſed, it maketh great diſturbances and diſcontents of many, in effect miſerable.</p>
               <p>Therefore there is no ſtirring of our Mint up nor down, for the reaſons aforeſaid, no gain to the Common-wealth, but infallible loſs to ſome parts, heart burning &amp; diſcontent, fit to bring in a foraign Enemie will enſue the tampering with the Mynt.</p>
               <p>Therefore I conclude this point, that there is no ſafe way but to ſtand conſtant at home, change with the changer abroad in matter of Commerce, and ſtand conſtant at home, which can no wayes be done, or known &amp; effected, but by the tables of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change mentioned in the Law of <hi>Edward</hi> the 3, known and put in Execution ever ſince in good times of Government; So it was in the time of <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And firſt to prove the Merchant-Exchange unequally carried, is the Efficient cauſe of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting our Monie; give me leave to know, whether plenty of Monie make our priſes of every thing to riſe, and ſcarcity of Monie makes ſmall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115190:10"/>prices, which no man I think will deny, and that Commodities are prized according to the goodneſs of the coyn, or to what end ſerveth fine Gold and Sylver, If it be not to prize all things.</p>
               <p>And if in our commerce with other Nations, we do give more fine Gold or Sylver then we receive or undervalue our coynes in commerce with others, it is a ſufficient out-let, or way to carry out our Monie or Bullion, when thereby thoſe that perceive the advantage to be had, ſhall leave the true uſe of trading in Merchandize, and turn Monie Merchants or Exporters of Bullion or Monies; for no Laws are prevalent againſt gain.</p>
               <p>And if we do not carry an equall hand with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rainers, in preſerving and encreaſing our Monies (as forraigners doe) we ſhall in ſmall time under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value our commodities for want of Monie, and conſequently overballance our trade in price or quality; and continuing the ſame courſe, ſend out our Monies in change for commodities, and have no more commodities then we had before, which courſe will infallibly impoveriſh the Nation excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly; and when there is want of Monie, or waſting of Bullion, the Commodities of the Nation, Wool, and all other home commodities will fall in price; the commodities falling, rents will fall accordingly; when rents do fall by ſuch a neceſſity, the neceſſity ſpreads it ſelf over the Land, and Tenants having taken leaſes at inhanced prizes of Country-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, not knowing the Efficient cauſe of this change of prices, will lay the cauſe on the Land-Lords, and grow in hatred towards them, not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115190:10"/>knowing how to hold their Farmes, nor what to doe when they give them over.</p>
               <p>This is a fearfull effect that followeth the want of a convenient ſtock of Monie to maintain the prices, and to beat or maintain our home-commerce proceeding from forrain cauſes, and not from Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owners, or Tenants at home.</p>
               <p>So it followeth, that thoſe that look to the home cauſe, as evil-making or Dying of our manufactu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or ſuch like, do not amend the matter, or raiſe the prizes; ſo long as there is no more Monie, to make the prices any greater. For it is infallibly true much Monie, much price; little Monie, little price: and it is as true, that inhancing of Goldor Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in <hi>France,</hi> will draw our Monies into <hi>France,</hi> as is before ſaid.</p>
               <p>But there is a more ſecret way which hath bin practiſed by Merchants and Bankers, and long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued; a biting or Canker-eating Uſury upon us: namely, the Merchandizing-Exchange which at the firſt was deviſed for good uſe, and moderate gain to the lender, and ready diſparch to their affaires, and for the avoiding of hazard importage of Monie, as aforeſaid which being abuſed, is turned into ineſtimable loſſe and damage to this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, with whom it is not underſtood in generall, by the Merchants that uſe it, as here they doe not, but take it upon truſt from the Bankers.</p>
               <p>Whereas amongſt the Dutch, it is ſo commonly known, that ſome women do know it, and I my ſelfe do know one (now an Engliſh Lady) that is skilful in the buſineſſe of Merchant-Exchange; and the <hi>Dutch</hi> are ſo wiſe that they will have banks amongſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115190:11"/>themſelves, and no forrain banks do fit down their; becauſe they ſee, that the gain of foraine bankes returns not profit to the Dutch, but to themſelves. I could wiſh that this were reſented by us.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe the gain that was gotten by forraign Bankers, was certified by 25 Selected Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners in King <hi>Iames</hi> his time to be an immenſe loſſe to this Nation: miſtake me not I pray, I do not ſpeak againſt Exchange, but againſt the carrying of our Monies out of our Land, by the Exchange unequally carried by ſtrangers, who are the rulers of it.</p>
               <p>My deſire is, that every Prince or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth might have the ſole uſe of their own Monies, within their Dominions; and for that cauſe, with other forerecited cauſes, was the Merchant Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change deviſed in old time, returning value for value with uſance according to reaſon for forbearance; and ſo might our Exchange of <hi>England</hi> (grounded upon the ſame reaſon) be continued and the Law of the land commands the ſame. The true valuation of Monie, makes the price of exchange for every place whereſoever we have to doe, and the want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and putting into uſe this Myſterie of comparing of our coines with the coines of others, value for value, bringeth in the abuſe and an ineſtimable dammage to this Common-wealth, for we ought to Examine and compare our weight and fineneſſe aforeſaid, with the weight and fineneſſe of other Countries, and the fineneſſe of our Standard as aforeſaid, with the fineneſſe of the Standard of the Monies of other Countries. And if we differ not with them in the proportion between the Gold
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115190:11"/>and Silver, then may our Exchange goe at one price both for Silver and Gold: the valuation of each Countryes Monies, being taken according to weight and fineneſſe, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>And if the proportion of gold and ſilver of other ſtrange Monies (as now in <hi>France</hi>) do differ from ours, then muſt we have two diſtinct valuations, one for Gold, and another for the Silver; and hereby ſhall we find how much fine Silver or Gold our pound Sterling containeth, and how much of other monies <hi>France, Germany, Low Countryes,</hi> or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, wee are to have to countervaile the ſame in the weight and fineneſſe anſwerable to ours. Whether it be by Pound, Crown, Ducket, or Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, giving always Value for Value, which amongſt Merchants is called <hi>Par.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The due and equitable courſe in Exchange being abuſed, and through the ignorance of Merchants, and neglect of the State (not examining the truth) but taking the price of Exchange upon truſt from the Bankers, who rule the price of Exchange, this trade of Exchange is become very deceiveable, and dammageable to our Nation; the Merchant making his accompt from the price of Exchange as it goeth when he uſeth it, and not from the true par or equality required. And from hence groweth the loſs of our monies, and the Exchange is become predominant over our monies, as monies do rule commodities, and is the efficient cauſe of this over-ballancing of commodities in price aforeſpoken of, and conſequently of the decreaſe of wealth, and exportation of our monies, when we were driven thereby to give as much of our native commodities
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115190:12"/>for forein commodities, as we did before the abuſe, and monies to boot, to fulfill the ſame quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity.</p>
               <p>This Exchange is made properly by Bills, when monies delivered ſimply here in <hi>England,</hi> and Bils delivered or received again for the payment thereof in ſome other Country beyond ſea; Or, when the like is done beyond the ſeas, and mony received here in <hi>England,</hi> and that upon a certain price a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon between party and party, which is term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Price of Exchange: whereof the Merchant, or rather the Bankers have the only and whole diſpoſing, and buy and ſell their commodities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond ſeas accordingly; without that, few or none of them do look into the nature or inward value of the Exchange, but only to the preſent object, which is to know how the price goeth at the time when they have occaſion to deal therewith, either in taking up, or delivering out monies by exchange: Whereas, if they will be true Exchangers indeed, they muſt know perfectly the weight and fineneſs of every Countries coin, thereby to render every one his juſt and due proportion as beforeſaid; that is, <hi>par pari referre,</hi> with conſideration to the Lender according to the time agreed upon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115190:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>ANd becauſe I have heretofore attributed the ruling of the Exchange to the Bankers, rather then to the general common Merchants; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoveth me, for the enlightning of all mens under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and further illuſtration of the buſineſs of Exchange, to ſhew what a Banker is.</p>
               <p>A Bank is properly a Collection of a great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of ready monies of a Province,
<note place="margin">Banker, what.</note> Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, or City, into the hands of ſome perſons licenſed and eſtabliſhed thereunto by publique Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, erected with great ſolemnity in the view of all the people and inhabitants, ſhewing great ſtore of gold and ſilver as belonging to the perſons ſo eſtabliſhed; which is to them an attractive, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade and allure the common people to bring their mony into theſe Bankers hands; ſo that theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or Bankers do become (as it were) the general ſervants or Caſhiers of that City, Province, or Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>The Bankers have their Factors or Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie in the chief places of Chriſtendom, and do keep accompt with every man of whom they have received any mony into their bank; and generally all men of wealth, that be Merchants, are deſirous to pleaſe them, and to bring their monies into the bank, in regard of double and treble credit they give to their Compartners, which they do by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation, without laying out of the bank any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Such, and greater devices have they, and many others too long to recite, the mony ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115190:13"/>in the Bankers hand, is employed by them to other uſes; as, to engroſſing of foreign Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities to <hi>Englands</hi> prejudice, and ſuch like feats, making money to ebb and flow when and where they pleaſe; and to that purpoſe the heads of every Bank do ſet price, and agree upon it by common conſent at their <hi>Ferias</hi> or general Fares for monies only; and ſtill their eye or devices tend to the beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of our Engliſh, and raiſing of their native commodities: which cunning our Merchants do not countermand, as in old time, when the Staplers that were intruſted with our ſtaple-commodities, were ſworn to advance the Engliſh commodities to their power, and alſo to bring in to this Nation a fifth part of their <hi>Exitus</hi> in mony. But as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the point of Exchange, it is moſt certain, that neither difference of weight, fineneſs of ſtandard, or valuations of monies, can be a true cauſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting our monies, ſo long as a due courſe is holden in Exchange, which is <hi>par pari referre.</hi> But this due courſe being abuſed, cauſes (as aforeſaid) our monies to be exported, and makes ſcarcity thereof, which abateth the price of our common commodities, and on the contrary ſide advanceth the price of the foreign commodities, by reaſon of plenty of money there encreaſed by ours ſent thither.</p>
               <p>But to this may be objected, If this be true (as it is very likely) then it would follow, that our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities would be alſo dear, where the plenty of money is. True it is, it would be ſo, but that they have two crafty devices to prevent the riſing of our commodities. One is, our Merchants being
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115190:13"/>takers of mony here to pay there, they know our Merchants muſt ſell, and do proffer their price according to the price of the goods in-bought, which they know as well as they that bought them; and alſo they have toleration of monies to paſs far above their value with them, and to the greater tranſportation of ours, and hindrance of importa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any to us.</p>
               <p>Therefore to conclude, there is no remedy but in the watch of the Exchange, to preſerve our own at home, and an ample trade of woollen commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, together with the ſetting of our poor on work, which live idly without employment. Theſe will advance the ballance.</p>
               <p>An high Exchange hindreth monies to come from the Eaſt, diverts the Royals of eight and Bullion that comes from the Weſt, and hindreth employment at home.</p>
               <p>A low Exchange exporteth our monies <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> for gain whereof neither high nor low is advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, but prejudicial to us; only a mediocrity is the beſt, which cannot be known but by the <hi>Par</hi> made known in Tables, expreſſing the <hi>Par</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the law of <hi>Edward</hi> the 3. and a Watch for the obſerving of that law (which hath been a long time neglected) giving leave to plenty or ſcarcity, as neceſſity or plenty inviteth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and is moſt agreeable to right and equity to all men: Which otherwiſe carried, the Stranger hath three wayes of exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, namely, by commodities, monies, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change; and there are but two ways of importati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely, Commodities and Exchange, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by cometh a notable over-ballancing of foreign
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115190:14"/>commodities: And be aſſured, the gains to be ſought upon monies, doth impeach the gains to be had upon our commodities abroad, and beateth down our prices at home; and our commodities being beat down, is a great cauſe of carrying out our monies, to fulfil or equal the ballance.</p>
               <p>The monies exported (as now they be) cauſeth increaſe of money and prices beyond ſea; ſo that our Merchants buying dear there, muſt ſell dear here, which bringeth a very great overballancing, and cauſeth us to feed upon our native ſoil, giving the benefit thereof to ſtrangers: whereas Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſhould live upon the gains of our home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities, being ſold to other Nations; and now our Merchants are driven to ſeek their gain upon foreign commodities, witneſs the Prices of Wines and other foreign commodities, to the great prejudice of our own Country; wherein, though the Merchants be gainers, yet the Commonwealth beareth the loſs, and they feed upon their mothers belly.</p>
               <p>More ſpecially in prices of foreign Commodities growing daily upon us, through neglect of our State not regarding it; what, and how much foreign prices have exceeded ours in growth, the old Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants can beſt tell, and is eaſie to be known: I do believe the Foreigners have exceeded us a fourth part, or more, within my memory, our monies ſtill remaining the ſelf-ſame, Five ſhillings to the ounce; and here conſiſteth the overballancing aforementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned. If the foreign Commodities which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed ſo ſoon to dung, ſhall mount in value, and the ſolid Staple-commodities of our Land ſtand,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115190:14"/>and not increaſe in price according to theirs,
<note place="margin">This is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the State to know.</note> 
                  <hi>certes</hi> this Land is very negligent and unprofitable to it ſelf. This is one point (I humbly conceive) doth call for a conſideration of State, amongſt many others, in the ballance of trade, to be conſidered.</p>
               <p>So then, give me leave to intimate this that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth by the abuſe of Exchange, four manner of ways.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By the ſcarcity of monies, cauſed by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal Exchange, which cauſeth home-commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to ſell cheap.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By the gain ſought upon monies, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would be ſought upon commodities.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By an high Exchange with us, which cauſeth men to deliver that mony by exchange in nature of trade, which otherwiſe by them might be employed upon our commodities; or by a low exchange, which cauſeth exportation of our monies.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By raſh ſale of our commodities by young Merchants and others, that are driven to pay mony taken up upon Exchange here in <hi>England</hi> to keep them doing, hereby ſpoiling the market of others.</p>
               <p>Foreign commodities on the contrary are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced four manner of ways.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Through plenty of monies in other countries, which maketh generally things dear; which plenty is increaſed by our monies, to our hurt every way.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By a high Exchange beyond ſeas, whereby men are inclined to buy foreign commodities; and by a low Exchange with them, when there are not akers up of money, and therein our exceſſive uſe of them doth encourage them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By toleration of monies, beyond ſeas, to go
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115190:15"/>current far above their value; for by the alteration of monies, the price of commodities doth alter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; and this toleration being a hinderance for the importation of monies, cauſeth the greater quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of foreign commodities to be brought over at a dear rate.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For that the principal commodities of Silks, Velvets, Fuſtians, and ſuch like, are ingroſſed by the Bankers (as aforeſaid) that ſell them at their pleaſures. Theſe ways conſidered, muſt needs bring an overballance in our trade (in value) to the loſs of Five hundred thouſand pounds a year.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>THus we may conſider how the Banker, and every one of our ſelves do uſe, or rather abuſe the Exchange, making it a trade for monies, and making that a biting Uſury, which was invented for ſpeedy Commutation, eaſe, ſafety, and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate gain to the Lender and Merchant-borrower indifferently.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, you may ſee merchandizing-exchange ruleth monies, as monies ruleth commodities; and that is fully proved, when we ſhall find viſibly that one piece of money of one ſort and kind of Coin hath two prices and two valuations at one time, exchanging the place only, or Country; as for example, you have a Piece of 20<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> and beyond the ſeas you may ſee the ſame piece paſs between man and man (in ſome place) for 22<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> in ſome other place at 24<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> and in <hi>France</hi> at 26<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> at one and the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115190:15"/>time, and mony willingly goeth where it is moſt made on: And whether they work upon coined mony, or valuing the ounce or pound at a higher price then their neighbour-Princes, if it be not carefully looked unto, it worketh the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and one remedy preventeth both.</p>
               <p>Wherefore our Merchants having no care nor regard of this, I humbly conceive it behoveth our State (which you repreſent at this time) to have a ſpecial care unto it, leſt the want of mony, when you ſtand in moſt need of it (now flying away from you) continue the fall of all home-commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, and your rents and livelihood to fall with it, which will be the undoing of your Tenants, the impoveriſhing of all men, turning up of your Farms and Grounds throughout the whole Nation in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, which in truth is the Mother of commotion and rebellion, procured through a generall decay of all eſtates. Every man being ready to ſtrike the next above him; and theſe be the fearful effects that follow an unequall Exchange: and for truth, the the common courſe of the Merchant-Exchange is unknown to moſt Merchants, and almoſt all men elſe, exceping ſome few, that uſe it for their private and unconſcionable gain, to the loſſe of the Comon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, like unto the Cancer or to the diſeaſe called the wolf, eating and conſuming the boſome that bred it.</p>
               <p>Give me leave (before I explain the remedy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived) to inform you, that if any to delude time, wil oppoſe or contradict, that unequal Exchange is prejudiciall to the Common-wealth, it is yeilded unto by common conſent of all hands, Merchants
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115190:16"/>and others, that unequall Exchange is prejudiciall to the ſtate, when it was controverted and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in King <hi>Iames</hi> his time, at what time he appointed 50 Commiſſioners for trade to ſit weekly in <hi>Haberdaſhers-hall,</hi> whereof one beſides my ſelf is ſtill living, called Sir <hi>George Stroud,</hi> then a Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Merchant. Whereupon it followed, that for the prevention of publique loſſe to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, a parity or equaility of Exchange ſhould be made known to all men, that had occaſion to uſe it, having regard to the forbearance, according to the time and place, which is moſt juſt and equall for all men, both Denizens and ſtrangers.</p>
               <p>To this Exception will be taken, unleſſe I doe explain my ſelf, allowing and graunting for truth, that plenty or ſcarcity of Monies to be given or taken up, doth beare a ſway, as it is upon the ſtatute of uſury,</p>
               <p>If there be plenty of Monies, they will be lent under the ſtatute; and if there be ſcarcity, there will be more given for the loan then the ſtatute allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, by ſome covert means or other; for in truth, the good uſe of the Merchandizing Exchange, is none other but a ready way of borrowing for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, without ſureties or delay to be executed; which moderately uſed, without exceſſive biting uſury, is both profitable and commendable for all Merchants to uſe, as their occaſion requireth; but if it be unequally or abuſively carried, may be juſtly called the Canker of <hi>Englands</hi> Common wealth. And let no Merchant think, but that I am their friend in wiſhing them eaſe and remedy therein, that it be not carried at the will of the banker, as it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115190:16"/>is but that it may be uſed according to the Antient Law of the Nation Extant and the practiſe of Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> for the ſame, which Law and Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation will appear upon the debate of the buſineſſe; If you pleaſe to take order.</p>
               <p>As alſo the demonſtration of the tables mentioned in the ſaid Law of <hi>Edward</hi> the 3<abbr>
                     <hi>d</hi>
                  </abbr>, one for Gold, and another for Silver, as I have ſeen the like in my time, reſpectively expreſſing the value of every peice of Gold or Silver Coyn with whom we have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, ſeverally compared with our pound Sterling; whereby the Equalitie is demonſtrated to every Merchant, that will follow the tables of Exchange, to avoid the daunger of the Law.</p>
               <p>And, becauſe forraign Coines are daily ſubject to alteration in fineneſſe or valuation, after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation is once made, it behoveth that there be (and it is no hard matter) an obſervant watch, or diligent eye over thoſe places of commerce and Mynts, to ſend intelligence hither to the Guardian of the tables, to alter the tables immediately in that point, and to keep conſtant at home, which will be a ſufficient guide to defend us from forraign wrong by any. This table of demonſtration once made, will be far more eaſie to underſtand, then any Pen or Tongue can expreſſe. This being done and obſerved, that the forraign Banker or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changer doe us no harm, in a ſmall proceſſe of time, our Ballance of trade will recover it ſelf again, and we ſhall have God willing a conſtant thrift to attend the labours of our Common-wealth, and not to be wrought upon by any biting uſury, by ſhifts or interval of time, to waſte or Exhauſt our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115190:17"/>treaſure or conſume the ſtock of ourcommonwealth that ſhould maintain the prices of our native com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities; our rents and artizens; as ſundry times in my memory it hath done. But what a Nation or Commonwealth have we, that is able to beare the loſſe of ſo much Coin as we have loſt, and departed from us within few years, that might have bin ſaved and had it bin ſaved, would have enabled us to ſend out a Portion of ready Monie yearly for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing of trade, or other worthy undertakings, as Herring-Buſſes, or ſuch like.</p>
               <p>The ſumms of Gold and Silver Mynted within theſe 10 years and now ſtoln out again, and wanting, may give the State ſatisfaction thereof by the Records of the Mynt, to be had at your command, to the unſpeakeable loſſe of the Common-wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP VI.</head>
               <p>THe tables of Exchange being put in uſe for our ſafety or ſafeguard it followeth then (as good husbands uſe to do) that we take accompt of the thrift of our common-wealth to ſee yearly how we doe thrive or goe backwards, Alſo to know by what ways our waſting commeth &amp; thence to diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inguiſh what ſeverall trades is beneficiall to our Common-wealth or not, and to ſet redreſſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly if occaſion require it, which is no new thing but an Antient practiſe as might be manifeſted; the generall ballance of trade being caſt up and found defective a light in the ballance, It behoveth us then to look what particular trade or commodityes be dammageable or hurtfull to our Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115190:17"/>and to ſet redreſſe. Firſt, then that trade or Merchant that carrieth out ſuperfluities or thoſe commodities wee abound in, and bring in the commodities that we want for them; that is a good trade or Merchant and deſerveth to be nouriſhed countenanced and maintained therein, and thoſe that doe contrary better ordered.</p>
               <p>Now who knoweth not that we abound in Wool and Woollen commodities, Tinn, Lead, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other things, which I name not, who knoweth not what we want of our own but muſt have it from without us, namely Gold, Silver, Iron and Steele, per conſequence it followeth that thoſe Merchants that bring in thoſe ſaid commodities we want, are moſt to be nouriſhed and fauoured before others that doe the contrary.</p>
               <p>But how or by what means is this trade of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant diſcovered, but by the Antient way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining the ballance of trade of late yeares, almoſt grown out of uſe, but it was diſcovered in the latter time of King <hi>Iames,</hi> there was one imployed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the unlawfull export of Wool, out of the port of <hi>Boſton,</hi> which was diſcovered by the cuſtom books of <hi>Boſton,</hi> though the wool were uncuſtomed: Where finding two ſhipps, one a ſtranger, and the other a <hi>Boſtoner,</hi> to come and goe often with little fraught, were more narrowly looked into and found to be faulty, and the offenders cenſured in the Star-Chamber, the other Shipp of <hi>Camphire</hi> came no more to <hi>Boſton;</hi> ſo by deligent ſearch might forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den goods and unlawfull trading be diſcovered: If the ſtate would encourage and recompence the Watchman and diſcoverers of abuſes. This watch
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115190:18"/>of the ballance of trade was alwayes obſerved by the prudent Lord <hi>Burley</hi> Lord <hi>Treaſurer</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to what other end, was all the port bookes of this Nation, brought into the Cuſtom houſe of <hi>London,</hi> and from thence once, A year tranſmitted with the cuſtom-bookes of <hi>London</hi> into the Kings remembrancers Office in the Exchequer; where one groſs ſum of all the Kingdoms <hi>Exitus</hi> and <hi>Introitus</hi> of Trade might be known, and of all the Goods both inward and outward bound and the value of both accompted, thereby to know whether we were buyers or ſellers, winners or loſers; for it behoveth the Father of a Family to be a ſeller, and not a buyer; and if it be found that we ſell more then we buy, we doe well; if otherwiſe, it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us to look about us.</p>
               <p>As in generall, a view may be had of our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique thrift; ſo in every particular Trade their walk being obſerved, it may be known what Trade brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in, or forceth in Money, or ſuch things as we want, for therein lieth the thrift of our Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; and ſo on the contrary, what Trade forceth out our Moneys, and per conſequence imbaſeth our commodities.</p>
               <p>This publique Thrift or reformation, as I humbly conceive would not be held in myſterie, but made more common and eaſie to every intelligent Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, becauſe he is in ſome fort intereſſed in the ſame for the advancement of the Publique good, and therin his own particular is intermixed. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am bold, and humbly commend the generall or theorical ſtudies of the Merchandizing exchange, and the balance of Trade unto your Wiſdoms to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115190:18"/>be regarded: and for theſe purpoſes, the keeping and the obſervance of the balance of Trade will be found very uſefull.</p>
               <p>There be alſo other things to be met with in the publique thrift, which for the preſent I forbeare, which before I have done or finiſhed my intended diſcourſe, I purpoſe to enter upon, if it pleaſe God, notwithſtanding the diſpute that may ariſe by them, that would endeavour to fruſtrate this buſineſſe; for private gain never wanted colours, and pretexts to ſtupefie or inveagle the underſtandings of ſuch as have not bin verſed therein.</p>
               <p>Give me leave, I pray, you to repeat one thing twice, though the ſame have bin in effect ſaid before for the better illuſtrating what hath bin ſaid to thoſe that were never ſeene nor ſtudyed any thing herein.</p>
               <p>It is a ſure tenent or maxime that it is neceſſary for our Common-wealth to keep conſtancy in our Mynt at home, ſo is it as neceſſary to change with the changer in all forraign Coines either Gold or Silver, reducing all foraign Coynes to a par or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality with our conſtant Coynes; and to that end in antient times, there was a paire of Tables ſet forth, expreſſing the ſame demonſtratively the one for Gold, the other for Silver Coynes, with whom we had to deale beyond ſeas. The French Crown did anſwer to ſix of our ſhillings: our unite to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain 3 French Crownes and a Third, ſo the Dutch Ryder, although it goe here but for 21 ſhillings, it is of equall value to our Unite, ſo as all forraign Coynes, ſeverally reduced to our Coynes, did ſhow and expreſſe what was to be given and allowed between ſtrangers and us in accompts, which is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115190:19"/>called the Merchant Exchange, this equality once known and expreſſed, as aforeſaid we may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived 3 manner of wayes,</p>
               <p>Firſt if we watch not forraign Mynts, by the ſheeres in coyning, whereby it may come to want in weight, although it were of equall fineneſſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly by putting in more Allay or Copper into their Monies, which is not perceived or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, how much, but by tryall in the fire, in mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome part and refining it and comparing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of pure Silver, to the like quantity of our Monies refined as theirs was.</p>
               <p>Thirdly without leſſening or embaſing to call any of their ſpecies higher up, a way commonly uſed in forraign parts called denomination, which muſt be watched and prevented by new expreſſions as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, ſo often as there ſhall be cauſe, by ſuch as the Lord <hi>Protector</hi> and his Council ſhall depute, for that purpoſe moſt proper for the Council of the Mynt affaires, I humbly conceive, this is a ſure way of preſerving our Coines at home with good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward giving to the diſcoverers of exporters of Gold and Silver, for there will alwayes be ſome of thoſe offenders, even if it were made Fellony, for once it was ſo, yet availed not: good recompence is far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then life. This is a ſure way, or the beſt can be of preſerving our Gold and Silver at home, without which the Bankers both forraigners and domeſtick have power to deceive our Common-wealth and leſſen our common ſtock of Gold and Silver, which will turne to a fearfull effect in time, and in few words, not to be expreſſed and double loſſe when the ballance of trade is againſt us to our loſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115190:19"/>with an unequal Exchange; and that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try or particular Trade that gains the Ballance gets our mony, be it friend or enemy: And if we loſe both wayes, how ſhould we long ſubſiſt without home poverty and Canker-eating conſumption?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>WHereas I propoſed five things to be uſeful to this Commonwealth: the two firſt, unequal Exchange and Ballance of trade, being in ſome meaſure laid open, the third is (to wit) a Bank and a Banker. What they be, is declared; but the feats and activities of the Bankers are not touched tending to their private gain, which is an enemy to the publique: For the moſt part all Corporations be hurtful to the Publique, if not overſeen by the States ſupreme government that preſerveth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth the publique good. But for and by this that hath been ſaid of the Bank, this reaſon may be given, <hi>Contrariorum contraria ſunt ſequentia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. A Bank of Foreigners was and is moſt hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to us in receiving from us the increaſe or loan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony given to the Bankers by thoſe that dealt by exchange with them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Ingroſſing of commodities, and indearing them to us, may be otherwiſe ordered, if we had a Bank of Engliſh goods and Engliſh ſubjects, that harm that was done by ſtrangers to our Nation, <hi>vice verſa,</hi> would be altered, and we defended; if
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115190:20"/>no further but ſo, it would redound much to our profit.</p>
               <p>If Banks of native Subjects were not both uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and beneficial to the Commonwealths wherein they live, they would not nouriſh them as they do both in <hi>Italy</hi> and the United Provinces. And for the preventing of the Dutch from indearing the Eaſt-Indie commodities, that would ſell them as they liſt unto us, our Eaſt-Indie Company is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by us. So the like it is with the Bank or Bankers, and for the aforeſaid reaſons allowable and profitable to have an Engliſh bank to prevent the forementioned enormities, if but ſo. But this being a policie exceeding my mean skill or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I humbly ſubmit it to the high Governors of the State to determine.</p>
               <p>And whereas, ſomething hath been heretofore objected againſt the having of a Bank in <hi>England</hi> in times paſt, that might now be anſwered: but herein <hi>Cynthius aurem vellit,</hi> and willeth me to be ſilent at this time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115190:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>THe fourth thing I humbly conceive is A ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Councel for Mint-affairs to be ſetled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, to ſit at the dayes appointed to give audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence concerning all affairs that concern the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Mint, or that may obſtruct or be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to the Mint, either by exportation, diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or conſumption, the great defrauders of the Mint, and to bring them all both offenders and acceſſaries to condign puniſhment according to the Law of the Land: And when this Court hath any cauſe concerning life or forfeiture of monies, to be aſſiſted with one or more of the Judges learned in the Law; and in the mean time to be a Court of inquiſition or preſentment, fitting the offenders for ſpeedy trial; for delay abateth the edge of the law, and experience telleth us that where the State doth not keep extraordinary watch in mony matters, the State is and will be abuſed, which is over-well known to the French and Dutch that we have no ſuch watch.</p>
               <p>And to make our Mint to flouriſh, the chief Officers of the Mint and Council would have a general knowledg of all the chief Mints and Mint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, and chief Bankers of Chriſtendom, which is a great point of State wiſdom, the greateſt point whereof is to foreſee that Bullion be had to keep the Mint going; and for that purpoſe to ſee that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115190:21"/>the Gold that cometh from <hi>Africk,</hi> and the Silver that cometh from the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> be brought to the Mint, and to uſe their endeauours to bring more, and to keep it when we have it. For that end, no penalty that concerneth the Mint to be remitted, the forfeitures to be great, and reward great to thoſe that diſcover the offenders, and the part given to the informers in no wiſe to be pardoned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> To keep the Goldſmiths to their trade to be Silverſmiths, and not to be Bankers or Caſhiers of mony for other men, which puts them in a way to deceive by culling of monies or other ſecret wayes of diminution of Coins, which other men know not. Likewiſe thoſe that give more for the Gold or Silver then the Mint, that is a foreſtalling of the Mint, in no State ſuffered, and frequently uſed here of late in the eye of all men. A circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect care would be had to the Examination of the Ballance of Trade in particular, likewiſe to have an eye obſerving of the Tables of Exchange when they be ſet out; Alſo to have a ſpecial regard in the time of peace what the French do here, for they do come and go often, and bring trifles for which they carry away our gold: It is not a ſmall ſum in the Ballance, that Pocket-commodities and things of ſmall bulk, being ſtollen without paying of Cuſtom, come to: Alſo to hunt out ſuch, were a good ſervice to the State. Laſtly, all commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties bought in with ready monies, as Currens, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, and Nuns works, or whatſoever carrieth monies or Bullion for it, by all means to be nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly lookt after for what cauſe ſoever. There be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115190:21"/>alſo divers wayes out of our proper ſelves to bring bullion to the Mint: but ſo long as we have not the retentive faculty, but do let our monies and bullion to paſs through as water through a ſive, we ſhall inrich others, and do our ſelves no good but harm.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>SO leaving this point of a Councel of Mint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affairs, I do proceed to the laſt of the five, namely <hi>Free-Ports.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Free-Ports.</note> of the inconvenience of not having Free-Ports of our own, it is well known, and I have in mine own time obſerved, that whenever wet ſeaſons of ſeed-time and harveſt do come, we have but little increaſe, and that little evil gotten; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth us of neceſſity to fetch and to buy our bread from the <hi>Hollander,</hi> or from <hi>Eaſt-Country,</hi> which we pay for in ready mony for the moſt part, The general law of all Nations permitteth to give mony for bread. This I have known divers times in <hi>England;</hi> not only our ready mony, but the poor folks treaſure, Pewter and Braſs, their utenſils ſold and ſent into <hi>Holland</hi> for bread, who have no bread for themſelves of their own growth, but buy it from cheap places in cheap years, and ſell it again to thoſe places that have ſcarcity of Corn or extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary cauſe for the uſe of Corn. So might we do if we had free Ports of our own ſubjects; the chief benefit would be to keep our monies at home,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115190:22"/>which we ſend out for Corn ſo often as we have wet and unſeaſonable years as aforeſaid, and feel the loſs of it many years after by reaſon of the want of our monies, which doth abaſe the prices of our home-commodities, to the uneſtimable loſs of our Commonwealth; which if we had free Ports of our own people, would return uneſtimable profit in lieu of our loſſes ſuſtained as aforeſaid, both in being ſtorers of many foreign Commodities we have not, and to ſend them forth again as the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> do in manner aforeſaid, giving and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſmall cuſtom for ſuch things as are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed or uſed within the Land. The increaſe of Shipping, and the wealth that is gotten by forein trade, is more then I can recount; the example of the <hi>Hollander</hi> may ſuffice for ſatisfaction herein.</p>
               <p>But to give equal priviledg to the Dutch to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in our Ports all winter, or when they will, and to be gone when they will, (otherwiſe then in diſtreſs of weather to give them harbor) is not only to give them that which they have not, nor can give the like to any other, open harbors all winter when theirs are frozen; and we have the benefit of many winds to go out and in, and they having fewer winds to go out and in, in <hi>Holland</hi>-Harbors, then we out of ours, and more danger in coming in and out then we in ours, witneſs the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent loſſes in the <hi>Texel;</hi> but alſo make our Ports their ſtore houſes, and become thereby Huxters amongſt us, which were too much unleſs they were incorporated one Nation with us, which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115190:22"/>thing is too great a buſineſs for me to treat or ſpeak of: Yet at leaſt thoſe that had the benefits of our Ports as free natural ſubjects, ſhould become our own ſubjects and plant their children amongſt us, and not to come hither to glean or gather our thyme, and make their hives in another place or country then ours. This were friendſhip above the Roman friendſhip, that were wont to grant their freedom not freely, but for a good ſum or price, as is verified of old.</p>
               <p>Therefore both the Seas and Ports being ours, theſe priviledges be more then ever was given by any free State or Commonwealth to any neighbor State that I ever heard of. Yet ſo well we love the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and firm alliance with them, that I believe there be many amongſt us of this mind, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſome do alleadge they will eat us out. If it be ſo that we be ſlothful and vitious, let Gods will be done, let the vertuous and laborious enjoy their labours, and poſterity enjoy and poſſeſs that which vitious drones have diſpoſſeſſed themſelves of: which I humbly conceive is juſt in the eye of God, and law of nature, if done without force. But if we ſhall admit them by way of courteſie to have free Ports without conditions with us, in ſhort time when they ſee opportunity they would be as unthankful for them, as they have been for the liberty of the Seas, as hath appeared by a Treatiſe divulged by them entituled <hi>Mare liberum,</hi> which was fully anſwered by learned <hi>SELDEN;</hi> and more particularly the Soveraignty of the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh ſeas proved by antient Records to belong to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115190:23"/>the Soveraign power of this Land, in a Treatiſe compoſed by the worthy Antiquary, Sir <hi>John Burroughs,</hi> called, <hi>The Soveraign of the Seas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude this point of Free-Ports, common reaſon confuteth the Liberty of the Seas: without government, both Sea and Sea-ports would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Receptacles of Thieves, Sea-robbers, and Pyrats, which would deſtroy Sea-traffick, if they be not maſtered and deſtroyed, which cannot be without government: Which being granted as a thing neceſſary to be at Seas as at Land, (not one over all Seas, for that is too vaſt a government to be under the rule of one, if it could be without injury or wrong to others) Who then ſhould? Even thoſe to whom the government moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belongeth: And who are thoſe? Even thoſe Principalities or Common-wealths who have the beſt Sea-harbors by ſite of nature, and near thoſe Seas, are fitteſt for the government of thoſe Seas adjacent; and withall the eldeſt preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the poſſeſſion of the government of thoſe Seas. Of which both Harbors, and poſſeſſion of Government of the Seas, <hi>Great Britany</hi> hath had the tuition and government, unleſs it were in the times when the Inlands of <hi>Great Britany</hi> were in Civil wars, and ſo the government of the Seas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came neglected.</p>
               <p>And to manifeſt this, begin we with</p>
               <p n="1">1. Our ſeveral Conflicts with, and Victory over the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115190:23"/>
               <p n="2">2. The times of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whoſe actions are freſh in memory, and her famous Conflict with the Spaniſh Navy, (by Gods ſpecial favour ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and never to be forgotten.)</p>
               <p n="3">3. The famous Navies and Victories of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, whereof the beſt and brief memory is his golden Coin (yet to be ſeen) called the Roſe-Noble, or Spur Royal, by his Image pictured thereon as the Stearſ-man of the ſhip, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Britiſh ſeas: Whoſe title of the Britiſh ſeas deſcended to him from <hi>Richard</hi> the Firſt, who in his way to the Holy wars (ſo called then) or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained new Laws, and confirmed the old, in the Iſle of <hi>Oloron,</hi> ever ſince called the Laws of <hi>Oloron,</hi> well known to Sea-men. He held the preſcription of the ſoveraignty of the Seas from <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt. And had the Seas been guarded in the times of <hi>Harold</hi> the Uſurper, which was neglected in the times of <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, <hi>William</hi> the firſt had not ſo eaſily entred <hi>England.</hi> So King <hi>Edgar</hi> had the ſoveraignty of the Seas, when he had eight Under-kings or Vice-roys to row the Barge, and he himſelf the Stearſ-man, and ſo entred <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</hi> Whoever had the maſtery of the Scas, <hi>Saxon</hi> or <hi>Dane,</hi> gained the Land. Even ſo it was in <hi>Julius Caeſar's</hi> time at his entry, teſtifying the excellencie of the Britiſh ſhips, which he after imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated in his future wars, leaving alſo a Memorial of the Britiſh government of the Seas and Sea-ports. The <hi>Britains</hi> were maſters of the Seas, and ſole Merchants; the <hi>Gauls</hi> being ignorant of the Inland of <hi>Britany,</hi> and ſo kept by the <hi>Britains</hi> from the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115190:24"/>knowledge of <hi>Britany,</hi> the <hi>Britains</hi> being maſters of the ſeas.</p>
               <p>What Nation can ſay ſo much as <hi>Great Britany?</hi> And therefore it behoveth us to regard our Seas and Sea Ports, and whom we plant in them, leſt neglecting them we become a prey and booty unto Strangers.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your <hi>Suppliant,</hi> as a weak Remembrancer, having according to my poor skill and ability paſſed over the Cinque-ports of the Profits of our Land, I hope my boldneſs herein may be excuſed, proceeding from the ardent deſire I bear to the welfare of our Country and Commonwealth.</signed>
               </closer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Etiam in magnis &amp; voluiſſe ſat est.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 5. l. 21. for <hi>then</hi> read <hi>this.</hi> p. 15. l. 9. for <hi>manufactritures</hi> r. <hi>manufactures.</hi> p. 28. l. 13. for <hi>ten</hi> r. <hi>twenty</hi> years. p. 28. l. 28. for <hi>a light</hi> r. <hi>or light.</hi> p. 29. l. 33. for <hi>Watchman</hi> r. <hi>Watchmen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115190:24"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
